<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of reverend Mr. Will. Whitaker, late minister of Magdalen Bermondsey, Southwark by Samuel Annesley.</title>
            <author>Annesley, Samuel, 1620?-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25473</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3237</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29041</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10798076</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10798076</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45958</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25473)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45958)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1375:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of reverend Mr. Will. Whitaker, late minister of Magdalen Bermondsey, Southwark by Samuel Annesley.</title>
                  <author>Annesley, Samuel, 1620?-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nevill Simmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whittaker, William, 1629-1672 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45958:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the FUNERAL Of Reverend M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> WILL. WHITAKER, Late MINISTER of <hi>Magdalen Bermondſey,</hi> Southwark.</p>
            <p>BY Samuel Anneſley, LL.D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, for <hi>Nevill Simmons,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Princes Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45958:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45958:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have more Arguments againſt, than for, the Printing of this Sermon; but yet there's one Argument, from time to time thundered in mine ears, which I muſt confeſs I cannot anſwer, and that is, if I will not Print it my ſelf, it ſhall be Printed without me, by the Notes taken at the preaching of it: And this was ſent me, by Word, by Writing; by Miniſters, by private Chriſtians: But this doth not (there's no reaſon it ſhould) make me think the better of the Sermon, as well knowing, it is the Excellency of the Perſon at whoſe Funeral 'twas preach'd, not any thing in it ſelf, that rendered it deſirable. I muſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal one reaſon I had againſt it, which is ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly pleaded for it; <hi>viz</hi> that I more privately preach't ſomething of it, ſome years before, after
<pb facs="tcp:45958:3"/>the Funeral of my precious and dear Friend Dr. <hi>Roger Drake,</hi> a Perſon of ſo tranſcendent worth, that were I an Orator fit for it, I could not forbear to ſet his Funeral Oration before this Funeral Sermon: Let it paſs therefore for a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable rarity (for I have not two ſuch Friends on this ſide Heaven) to gather a Noſegay off one Grave, to ſtrow upon another, (though the other doth not need it.) They were ſo intimate while waking, that the ſame Sheets may ſhrowd them now they ſleep in Jeſus. I ſhall not ſpeak much of either, where was nothing common, but every thing worthy of Wonder and Imitation. For the <hi>Doctor,</hi> conſider him every way, and his Worth was unexpreſſible. For his Perſonal Graces, during his forty years ſtanding in Chriſt, he was eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blameleſs, and ſingularly free from the defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Sin, and the buffetings of Satan; and above all this, his humility was unparallel'd. For his relative Piety, beſides the family-duties that are common to all ſerious Chriſtians, he kept a <hi>ſet-time</hi> of praying with his Wife every day. And for his way of inſtructing, reproving, convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and counſelling every perſon of his family, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and privately in his Study as occaſion required, praying with them ere he diſmiſt them, that his words might abide; I never heard the like of any
<pb facs="tcp:45958:3"/>other. For his worldly incomes, he ever laid by the <hi>tenth part</hi> for the poor, before he uſed any for himſelf. For his Miniſterial Excellencies, his engaging <hi>in,</hi> turning <hi>from,</hi> returning <hi>to,</hi> and diligence <hi>about</hi> the work of the Miniſtry, theſe are well known to thoſe that knew him; but will be ſcarce credible to thoſe that knew him not, and therefore I ſay ſo little of them. Thoſe that heard him pray upon any extraordinary occaſion, muſt be forc't to acknowledge, his praying <hi>by the Spirit,</hi> was not <hi>Phanatical.</hi> His Writings will be eſteemed while there are Books in the world, for the ſtream of piety and learning that runs through his <hi>Sacred Chronology.</hi> But the elevation of his Graces in his death-bead Sickneſs was moſt remarkable: he went out like one of the Lamps of the Sanctuary, with a ſweet perfume. I cannot tell you his <hi>Triumphs</hi> of faith, his <hi>foretaſtes</hi> of Heaven, his earneſt and holy Diſcourſe, his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirings of God, his unwillingneſs to retreat into the Wilderneſs, his charge to his Children, that they ſhould not dare to meet him at Judgement in an unregenerate ſtate, ſaying if they did, <hi>he ſhould laugh at them;</hi> and his ſealing of his Miniſtry to his Pariſhioners that viſited him. The laſt time I ſaw him, his Diſcourſe was ſuch of the love of God, that I expect not to hear ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:45958:4"/>another till I come to Heaven. But I'le add no more, only his dying words, which were <hi>[Jeſus take me, I am ready].</hi> I need ſay no more, and I could ſay no leſs, as his memory is, ſo let his Poſterity be bleſſed. My gleanings concerning this parallel Servant of Chriſt, you ſhall have them in the Sermon: that all I have, or can ſay, may provoke you to an holy emulation, and fit you to ſit down with them in the Kingdom of God, is the hearty prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Soul-ſervant, Samuel Anneſley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45958:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ZECHARIAH I. V, VI.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſe 5.</hi>
                     </bibl> Your Fathers, where are they? and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, do they live for ever?</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſe 6.</hi>
                     </bibl> But my Words, and my Statutes, which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded my ſervants the Prophets, did they not take hold of your Fathers? and they returned, and ſaid, like as the Lord of Hoſts thought to do unto us, according to our wayes, and according to our doings, ſo hath he dealt with us.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y only <hi>Preface</hi> ſhall be this. I never <hi>did</hi> before, I never <hi>ſhall</hi> again, preach <hi>to this Aſſembly:</hi> All of us that are <hi>now</hi> met upon this ſad occaſion, ſhall <hi>never</hi> meet more, till the general reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; it therefore concerns <hi>me</hi> to ſpeak, and <hi>you</hi> to hear, as thoſe that have one overture toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Heaven, which if it be loſt, it is loſt for ever.</p>
            <p>The Prophet begins this Book with the heads of a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45958:5"/>Sermon of <hi>Repentance,</hi> which he prefixeth as a Preface to his other Prophecies, both of mercy, and judgement. And that fitly, <hi>Repentance</hi> being the only preparative for Mercy, and the only means to eſcape Judgement. He enforceth his Exhortation to repentance, from the conſideration of Gods diſpleaſure againſt their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Verſe</hi> 2. and from the hope of his former fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to them, <hi>Verſe</hi> 3. and that they ſhould not imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate their Fathers in contemning of God, <hi>Verſe</hi> 4. for though their Fathers dye, and the Prophets that admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed them were all dead, yet the Word is perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in all ages, and the truth of it appeared in the effects, which are yet to be ſeen, <hi>Verſe</hi> 5, 6.</p>
            <p>I find a threefold Interpretation of the words; and though the laſt I ſhall name, is that which I conceive to be the right, yet I will not conceal the other two, and I ſhall tell you anon, why. Some take theſe words to be Gods inſulting over the Jews, as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Now bethink your ſelves what befell your Fathers, are they not all extinct, and deſtroyed?</hi> to which the Jews as it were anſwer, <hi>What do you tell us of our Fathers? what difference is between them and the Prophets that preached againſt them, are they not both dead?</hi> to which God as it were replyes, <hi>though they are both dead and gone, yet his word did not want its effects upon their fathers.</hi> This Expoſition is received by <hi>many,</hi> and thoſe that are <hi>moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond interpretation is that of <hi>Hierom,</hi> who takes this to be ſpoken of the falſe Prophets, as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Where are the Prophets that flattered your fathers with promiſes of happineſs? are not they, and your fathers both dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this third, which I take to be the genuine mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45958:5"/>of the words is this, as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers they are dead, and you cannot now tell how it fares with them: the Prophets were but men, and they are dead, neither can they live alwayes to preach, or to ſee their Prophecies fulfilled: but though your fathers are dead, their puniſhments ought not to be forgotten: and though the Prophets are alſo dead, their Prophecies are not to be buried with them: I appeal to your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and obſervation, did not the threatnings of the Prophets overtake your fathers, and catch them, as Huntſmen their prey, or one enemy another in ſlight, though they ſought to make their eſcape: and when they felt Gods hand upon them, then they were better adviſed, and then they began to come to the right knowledge of their eſtate: as</hi> Mal. 3.18. <hi>Then they diſcerned between the righteous and the wicked, then they felt the difference between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not!</hi> Thus <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Pemble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet <hi>Sanctius</hi> in his Paraphraſe layes my Text the faireſt for what I deſigned in the choice of it; bringing in the Prophet as it were thus enquiring, and adviſing. <hi>Where are thoſe fooliſh Parents, that enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained my meſſage with ſcorn and laughter, as if the threatnings would never reach them? and where are thoſe Prophets, that foretold ſuch hard things? Shall they live for ever, that they may daily admoniſh you? No truly; the time is coming wherein true Prophecie ſhall for a long time ceaſe, and therefore hear while you may, the Prophets Oracles.</hi> The ſhort reſult of the words is this.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45958:6"/>
               <head>DOCT. <hi>Though Miniſters dye, their meſſage is immortal: they ſhould deliver it, and people receive it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Were it not for overcharging your memories, I would have given it you thus;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seeing thoſe that are taught, and thoſe that teach them, are both mortal, but the Word of God is immortal, and will certainly overtake us in this world, and follow us into the next, it ſhould therefore be a prevailing ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to every one of us, to make the beſt uſe of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent help of Miniſters for our thorow turning unto God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>People <hi>dye,</hi> and Miniſters <hi>dye,</hi> but the Word <hi>lives.</hi> Men firſt or laſt ſhall feel that Word to be <hi>true,</hi> which they are moſt unwilling to believe to be <hi>ſo;</hi> and thoſe things to <hi>overtake</hi> them, which they moſt induſtriouſly put <hi>fartheſt</hi> from them.</p>
               <p>Chriſtians we deliver our <hi>meſſage,</hi> and we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led home to give an account to him that ſent us, men turn their backs upon the Word, and run away from it, and are never to ſeek for an excuſe, why they do no more regard it, but all this will not ſerve their turn; <hi>dye</hi> they muſt, and <hi>be</hi> judged they muſt, according to <hi>what</hi> they have heard, and <hi>how</hi> they have lived, and therefore it will be your wiſdom to turn to God, and make uſe of Miniſters while you have them. Alas, my Brethren, you may uſe us at your pleaſure (I do not mean you may lawfully do it, but you may really do it) and if your rejecting of our meſſage could but <hi>ſhake</hi> off your obligation, or <hi>fright</hi> your Judge from medling with you, you might vapour
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45958:6"/>over us, and count it a piece of Gallantry to out-face poor Miniſters, and to out-brave their meſſage; but <hi>how long</hi> will you be able to carry it? <hi>How ſoon</hi> may a burning Feavor <hi>cool</hi> your courage? and the <hi>King of Terrors</hi> change your thoughts? now is your <hi>hour,</hi> (alas, 'tis but an hour, a little while) and the power of your darkneſs, that will not endure the light. But, Sirs, be it known to you, your <hi>ſleepy</hi> conſciences ſhall be awakened, and your ſelf-flattering dreams ſhall have an end, then that Word which you counted as <hi>wind,</hi> ſhall kindle upon you as <hi>fire,</hi> and there will be no ſtanding before it. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.13, 14. Chriſt told his hearers, Luke 11.49. <hi>That the wiſdom of God ſaid, I will ſend them Prophets and Apoſtles; and ſome of them they ſhall ſlay and perſecute,</hi> &amp;c. Here's unſearchable wiſdom, which we cannot fully know the reaſon of, till we come to Heaven. In <hi>Jer.</hi> 26. you have an account of Gods Commiſſion to <hi>Jeremy,</hi> the Spiritual Rulers entertainment of it, and the Prophets preſſing of them to a better reception of his meſſage, for their own ſake. Verſe 2. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, ſtand in the Court of the Lords houſe, and ſpeak unto all the Cities of</hi> Judah, <hi>which come to worſhiop in the Lords houſe, All the words that I command thee to ſpeak unto them; diminiſh not a word.</hi> The ſubſtance of his meſſage was the ſame with ours, [the ſame in all Ages] <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> or <hi>periſh.</hi> We have no authority to abate any thing; our Commiſſion allows us not to alter a word, by way of <hi>indulgence</hi> to ſin, or <hi>diſpenſation</hi> from du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; if you like not the terms, quarrel not with us. Verſe 8. <hi>Now it came to paſs, when</hi> Jeremiah <hi>had made an end of ſpeaking all that the Lord hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him</hi> (it is well that they would give him the hearing, and that they would hear him ſpeak out)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45958:7"/>
                  <hi>that the Prieſts and the Prophets, and all the people took him, ſaying, thou ſhalt ſurely dye.</hi> Verſe 12. <hi>Then ſpake</hi> Jeremiah <hi>unto all the Princes, and to all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſaying, the Lord ſent me to propheſie againſt this City, all the words that ye have heard.</hi> Ver. 13. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now amend your wayes, and your doings,</hi> &amp;c. Verſe 14. <hi>As for me, behold, I am in your hand: do with me as ſeemeth good and meet unto you.</hi> Ver. 15. He doth as it were ſay, you may rid your hands of your <hi>Prophet,</hi> but you cannot do ſo of your <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> though the Prophet were <hi>dead,</hi> his word would <hi>live;</hi> and though you may ſhuffle through many tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral dangers, yet the Word of God will certainly overtake you according to that in 1 Kings 19.17. —<hi>Him that eſcapeth the ſword of</hi> Hazael, <hi>ſhall</hi> Jehu <hi>ſlay; and him that eſcapeth from the ſword of</hi> Jehu, <hi>ſhall</hi> Eliſha <hi>ſlay.</hi> That is, though you eſcape falling by a forreign War, and though you may ſhift for your ſelves in a Civil War, yet you cannot eſcape the Words taking hold of you. Nay, though you were ſuch Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> ſuch gyantly ſinners, that no man living durſt ſpeak to you, yet the Word of God will reach you. One Scripture-ſtory I commend to you, to this purpoſe; 2 Chron. 21.12. <hi>And there came a Writing to him from</hi> Elijah <hi>the Prophet, ſaying,</hi> &amp;c. Not that this Letter was written by <hi>Elias</hi> in Paradiſe, and ſent by the Miniſtry of Angels, as <hi>Menochius</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprets it, but plainly; the Prophet wrote this before his rapture; and left it behind him, to be delivered to <hi>Jehoram,</hi> after he ſhould have committed the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned abominations; we read a Prophecy of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> by name, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.2. which Prophecy was not accompliſhed till three hundred and thirty years after: Another of <hi>Cyrus</hi> by name, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.1. almoſt two
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45958:7"/>hundred years before the accompliſhment. The plain truth was this, this <hi>Jehoram</hi> would not endure a living Prophet to declare the truth unto him; and therefore that he might be the more <hi>convinced,</hi> and <hi>confounded</hi> for his wickedneſs, here's a Writing brought him from one that was then in Heaven. Theſe inſtances may ſerve for a Scripture-demonſtration, That though Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters <hi>dye,</hi> their meſſage is <hi>immortal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is your profit I aim at in treating of this Doctrine; that I may therefore be more diſtinct and particular, I will parcell it out into theſe following Propoſitions. <hi>And now Chriſtians, I do in the name of my Supream Lord and Maſter ſolemnly require ſuch attention, as becomes thoſe that ſhall feel this truth in both worlds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Propoſition 1. <hi>Thoſe that live in contempt of the Word, cannot out-live the power of it.</hi> Many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons live and dye in a ſelf-flattery, that the threatnings againſt <hi>their</hi> ſins (the ſins that they are reſolved to live in) ſhall never overtake them. How many are there that <hi>ſtudy</hi> to be Infidels, and <hi>ſtrive</hi> to be Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts; they would fain perſwade themſelves, that a Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture faith is but a fancy; and that God will never be ſo ſevere, as we report him; but, yet a little while, and they ſhall feel the contrary. Others hear the Word, and are at preſent ſtartled, but their convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wear off, and their ſenſe of duty dyes before them: Alas, Sirs, our obligations to duty do not ebb and flow according to our apprehenſions of it. The evil and danger of ſin doth not abate as we would have it. Ezek. 2.4, 5. <hi>They are impudent children, and ſtiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted: I do ſend thee unto them, and thou ſhalt ſay unto them, thus ſaith the Lord God. And they, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will hear, or whether they will forbear (for they are a rebellious houſe) yet ſhall know that there
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45958:8"/>hath been a Prophet among them.</hi> Beloved Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, I pray you conſider it, The way of ſin, is the way of the greateſt <hi>folly</hi> in the world; for men will indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly live in ſin, and as induſtriouſly avoid taking notice of Gods indignation againſt it; and becauſe <hi>they</hi> take no notice, they are willing to perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>God</hi> takes no notice of them. Yet theſe very perſons, when they are under any <hi>qualms</hi> of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and any tendency towards repentance, then they as induſtriouſly perſwade themſelves, God muſt <hi>needs</hi> take notice of them, and that a few gripes of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence muſt needs be mortification ſufficient. Why, Sirs, what do you make of God all this while? But what need I ask this queſtion, ſeeing the Word of God hath ſo plainly reſolved it. Pſal. 50.21. <hi>Thou thoughtſt</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>that I was altogether ſuch an one as thy ſelf.</hi> The ſinner thinks, while <hi>he</hi> hath a kindneſs for ſin, God muſt needs indulge it, and when <hi>he</hi> is never ſo little uneaſie under it, God muſt needs pardon it; while <hi>he</hi> winks at ſin, God muſt not ſee it; and when <hi>he</hi> never ſo ſlightly looks up for mercy, God muſt not deny it. Oh, how do poor Miniſters find this by experience! Thoſe that while they are well, all we can ſay will not move them: If they ſend for us when ſick, we muſt ſay nothing to diſcourage them; we are harſh, and uncharitable, yea, uncivil, and not fit to viſit a dying perſon, if we diſturb them with any cloſe queſtioning of their repentance. Oh, 'tis a piece of cruelty to thruſt the <hi>probe</hi> of the Word into their feſtered conſciences; we muſt take ſins forſaking of them, when they can no longer commit it, to be their forſaking of ſin: and though we with never ſo much tenderneſs ſuſpect their eſtate, and beg of them to take heed of dying in a miſtake, that will then ceaſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45958:8"/>to be cureable, yet ſuch language is not to be endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, we muſt (at leaſt) be diſmiſt with <hi>Felix</hi> his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, Acts 24, 25. <hi>Go thy way for this time, when I have a convenient ſeaſon, I will call for thee.</hi> But that ſeaſon never comes: one while ſuch melancholy (for ſo muſt all ſeriouſneſs be called) will hinder the working of his Phyſick, another while 'twill break his reſt, and ſo he muſt rather be let alone to go to Hell, than be troubled with directions how to get to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Well, in ſhort, think what you will of us, and of our errand, both in health and in ſickneſs; though you carry it, as if 'twere alwayes too ſoon, or too late for <hi>you</hi> to be <hi>ſerious</hi> in Religion; the warning we give you, will have its efficacy, one way or other, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.10, 11. if your hearts be not <hi>melted,</hi> they will be <hi>hardned,</hi> by the ſhining of the Sun of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; if you make it not your buſineſs to <hi>lay hold on eternal life,</hi> you cannot avoid it, but eternal death will lay hold on you.</p>
               <p>Propoſition 2. <hi>Though Miniſters dye, their meſſage ſhall ſurvive them.</hi> The authority and certainty of our meſſage doth not depend upon our uſage in the world, nor our going out of it. It is an eaſie matter to quarrel with the meſſenger, but it is impoſſible to evade the meſſage. We are as ſubject to death as other men, and what if I ſhould ſay (I ſpeak it by way of enquiry, not poſitively) 'tis worth while to conſider, <hi>Whether there be not fewer eminently faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters live to old age, than perſons of any other Calling whatſoever.</hi> They live more time (time worth the name of living) in <hi>one</hi> year, than others do in <hi>twenty:</hi> The keener the Knife, the ſooner it cuts the Sheath. Thoſe that run hard, are ſooneſt at the end of their race. But doth their meſſage dye with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45958:9"/>them? No ſure. What is ſaid of young <hi>Samuel,</hi> that lived to ſee his words verified, may be ſaid of thoſe that dye before they ſee any effect of them, 1 Sam. 3.19. <hi>The Lord was with him, and did let none of his words fall to the ground.</hi> Though men let them fall to the ground, God will not. 2 Tim. 2.9. <hi>I</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ſuffer trouble as an evil doer, even unto bonds, but the word of God is not bound.</hi> I know not why we ſhould reſtrain this to the liberty the Apoſtle had while in priſon to preach to thoſe that were preſent, and to write Epiſtles to thoſe that were abſent, but it may alſo refer to the power and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Word, that it never returns in vain to him that ſent it; thoſe to whom it is ſent, ſhall moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be the <hi>captives</hi> of his <hi>love,</hi> or of his <hi>wrath.</hi> And let me here put in one word for the comfort of believers, As God in juſtice fulfills <hi>threatnings,</hi> after the Miniſters, that publiſh them are dead; ſo God graciouſly fulfills <hi>Promiſes,</hi> after the Miniſters that declare them are dead. How many troubled ſouls are ready to conclude, upon the death of their ſpiritual Phyſitian, to whom (to their comfort) they have opened their grief; Oh now they have none to ſpeak to; now thoſe refreſhments they were wont to have ſhall ceaſe. No. Dear Chriſtians, fear it not; the Promiſes they have helpt you to apply, ſhall abide by you, and God will bring you into a profitable acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with others, that ſhall through grace help you to experiment, that ſpiritual Phyſick will not loſe its efficacy by the death of the Phyſitian. Chriſt encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> with this, that they ſhould reap, what the <hi>Prophets</hi> only lived to ſow, <hi>John</hi> 4.37, 38. So that whether you are <hi>glad,</hi> or <hi>ſorry,</hi> that God takes away your Guides, the words they have ſpoken in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45958:9"/>name of the Lord, ſhall to your <hi>ſorrow</hi> or <hi>comfort,</hi> certainly ſurvive them.</p>
               <p>Propoſition 3. <hi>Though perſons to whom God vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeth the Means of Grace, withdraw themſelves from under it, and remain willingly ignorant of their ſin and duty, yet the Word will overtake them, and find them out, and they muſt ſtand, or fall according to their entertaiment of it.</hi> How <hi>dexterouſly</hi> do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſons <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> themſelves out of their duty? and how <hi>induſtriouſly</hi> do others remain wilfully igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of it? little conſidering, that ſins of <hi>wilful ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance</hi> are in ſome reſpects <hi>worſe than ſins againſt knowledge: e. g.</hi> Sins againſt knowledge are many times ſtriven againſt, and ſo through grace more eaſily pardoned, than ſins of wilful ignorance, which are alwayes induſtriouſly committed, and never ſtriven againſt. Beſides, ſins of wilful ignorance are alſo ſins againſt knowledge: for there's ſo much knowledge and ſenſe of duty, that they think if they knew more, they muſt do otherwiſe, or their ſin would be aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, and therefore they ſhut their eyes againſt the light, that they may ſin more freely: So that here's ſinning againſt knowledge, in their wilful igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and ſo there's a double guilt, each kind of which is very dreadful. James 4.17. <hi>To him that knoweth to do good, and doth it not, to him it is ſin.</hi> Sin with a monſtrous aggravation. And <hi>Job</hi> 21.14, 15. for thoſe that ſay unto God, <hi>Depart from us: for we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes. What is the Almighty, that we ſhould ſerve him? and what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit ſhall we have, if we pray unto him?</hi> God an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers him, that for this his wilful ignorance, <hi>his eyes ſhall ſee his deſtruction, and he ſhall drink of the wrath of the Almighty. God will reward him, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45958:10"/>he ſhall know it,</hi> Verſe 19, 20. Do but ſee at what a rate men are willing to compound with God, ſo they might but keep their ſin. Mic. 6.7. <hi>Will the Lord be pleaſed with thouſands of Rams, or with ten thouſands of Rivers of Oyl?</hi> All this for one tranſgreſſion: A dear bought ſin ſure! but he'l not ſtick at more than all this: <hi>Shall I give my firſt born for my tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Scelus meum,</hi> my Rebellion; <hi>the fruit of my body for the</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>peccatum,</hi> my error, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake <hi>of my ſoul?</hi> Lord, if I may not compound with thee for greater provocations, yet I hope thou wilt compound with me for my leſſer ſins, the ſin that my ſoul is loth to part with, is but a little one: I'le do thee as much ſervice as ſhall make amends for ſuch a <hi>peccatillo,</hi> let me keep but this ſmall ſin, and I'le ſtick at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe. Wicked men will <hi>pretend</hi> well, and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> fair, and <hi>plead</hi> hard, ſo they may but keep their ſin, ſo God would but let them do <hi>what</hi> they have a mind to; but if not, they care not for hearing from him. Take notice of a doleful inſtance of this in a reſerved remnant, wonderfully delivered from ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſweeping Judgments; thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> I mean that were preſerved from the Sword, Famine and Peſtilence, by which ſo many were deſtroyed, that had eſcaped being carryed captive to <hi>Babylon,</hi> and were delivered from being carryed captive by <hi>Iſhmael:</hi> we might ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally think, the ſenſe of theſe mercies being ſo freſh, and preſent, they would be very much afraid of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing God, and that they would not venture upon a known ſin, to prevent danger. But ſee the ſtory, <hi>Jer.</hi> 42.2.—6. they would have the Prophet tell them from God what they ſhould do, when as they were before hand reſolved what they would do. Yea, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they are ſo impudent as to call <hi>God to be a true
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45958:10"/>and faithful witneſs</hi> to what they nothing leſs intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, than what they ſo ſolemnly profeſſed and pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. They ſeemed reſolved to do what ever God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, were it never ſo diſadvantageous and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to them: but when God forbids what they have a mind to, then <hi>Jer.</hi> 43.2. they ſay to <hi>Jeremy, Thou ſpeakeſt falſly: the Lord our God hath not ſent thee to ſay, Go not into</hi> Aegypt <hi>to ſojourn there.</hi> Whereas the plain truth is, had they not been reſolved even to pick a quarrel with God himſelf, they would never have propoſed a caſe ſo expreſly already determined in Scripture, as this was, Deut. 17.16. <hi>You ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to</hi> Aegypt—<hi>foraſmuch as the Lord hath ſaid unto them, ye ſhall henceforth return no more that way.</hi> Whence the <hi>Hebrews</hi> have a ſaying, That it is lawful to dwell in all the world, ſave in the Land of <hi>Aegypt:</hi> and therefore the Prophet might eaſily tell them, whence it was they pickt quarrels with the meſſage, Jer. 42.20, 21. <hi>Ye diſſembled in your hearts when ye ſent me unto the Lord your God, ſaying, pray for us unto the Lord our God: and according to all that the Lord our God ſhall ſay, ſo declare unto us, and we will do it.</hi> Verſe 21. <hi>And now I have this day declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to you, but ye have not obeyed the voice of the Lord your God, nor any thing for the which he hath ſent me to you.</hi> And when they were a little <hi>heated</hi> by the Prophets unwelcome meſſage, they plainly tell him, Jer. 44.16. <hi>As for the word that thou haſt ſpoken unto us in the name of the Lord, we will not hearken unto thee.</hi> When once it comes to this, 'tis time for God to tell them, Jer. 44.28. <hi>You ſhall know whoſe words ſhall ſtand, mine or yours.</hi> They ſhuffle all they can before they come to tell God to his face, they will not obey him, but God tells them all along what
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45958:11"/>they muſt truſt to, God will neither be <hi>flatter'd</hi> nor <hi>hector'd</hi> to any gratifying them in ſin.</p>
               <p>Propoſition 4. <hi>Former threatnings and the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them ſhould excite us to repentance, though the Prophets that denounc't the one, and the people that felt the other are dead and gone long ſince.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> tells the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of <hi>Sodoms</hi> caſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6. how God turn'd the Cities of <hi>Sodom and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah into aſhes, condemning them with an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, making them an enſample unto thoſe that after ſhould live ungodly.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Corinthians</hi> of <hi>Iſraels</hi> caſe, 1 Cor. 10.5, 6, &amp;c. <hi>With many of them God was not well pleaſed: for they were overthrown in the Wilderneſs. Now theſe things were our examples, to the intent that we ſhould not luſt after evil things, as they alſo luſted,</hi> &amp;c. Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, you have the Scripture Records in your hands, how God hath dealt with ſuch ſinners as <hi>you</hi> are: In the very ſins <hi>you</hi> are guilty of, you have inſtances of Gods diſpleaſure. Is God more favourable to ſin now than formerly? If he be not ſo quick in temporal ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, you have the more cauſe to fear eternal. God is <hi>infinitely</hi> holy, and cannot be <hi>leſs</hi> holy than he is, unleſs he ceaſe to be God, which is utterly impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. There's no way of getting off the guilt of ſin without repentance (in grown perſons I mean) the blood of Chriſt, will not do it without actual repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Chriſt himſelf tells you, that unleſs you will take warning by others, your ſelves may be made an example to others, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.1, 5. Thoſe againſt whom God ſeems moſt ſevere in this world, are not greater ſinners than others: <hi>But except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:45958:11"/>
               <p>Propoſition 5. <hi>The death of ſome Miniſters ſhould provoke us to make better uſe of all Miniſters, living and dying.</hi> And the ſpeaking to this, may ſerve for Application of all the reſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The death of bad Miniſters ſhould at leaſt ſtartle us.</hi> I begin with theſe, becauſe ſome take my Text to ſpeak of falſe Prophets, which though I think they miſtake, yet we may gather inſtruction from it, ere we reject it. Wicked Miniſters are Maſter-builders of the Synagogue of Satan; inſtead of attempting to break the heart with piercing convictions, they daub it over with untempered morter: Scripture they wrack 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) to ſpeak what the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt never intended: and they will put pillows un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their elbows, that they may ſin at eaſe. God chargeth them with hunting of ſouls, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.18. but 'tis not to ſave the ſouls alive that come to them; 'tis to <hi>deſtroy</hi> them, not to <hi>ſave</hi> them: whereas Chriſt employes his faithful Miniſters to be fiſhers of men, <hi>Luke</hi> 5.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to catch them alive, that they may <hi>live,</hi> and that <hi>with God</hi> unto eternity. Now for thoſe that ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked, by promiſing them ſalvation, though they turn not from their evil way, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.22. Thoſe ſpiritually blind Guides, and thoſe hood-winkt ſinners that are guided by them, ſhall both fall remedileſly into Hell. You that love your ſins, love ſuch Miniſters as will leaſt diſturb you in the proſecution of them, but how long can you, or any for you, huſh your conſciences aſleep? How long will theſe pleaſing dreams laſt? Thoſe that help them to caſt off the <hi>thoughts</hi> of death, cannot ſecure themſelves from the <hi>ſtroke</hi> of it. Methinks 'tis conſiderable, God made <hi>that</hi> Prophet who ſeduced another, to be the very Herald of Gods diſpleaſure for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45958:12"/>his being ſeduced by him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.18, 22. And <hi>Zedekiah</hi> that encouraged <hi>Ahab</hi> againſt the warning of <hi>Micaiah,</hi> muſt himſelf upon the iſſue of his falſe Prophecy ſeek to hide himſelf from <hi>Ahahs</hi> children and friends, who would ſeek to be revenged on him for the death of the King, and the overthrow of the Army, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.25. And <hi>Hananiah</hi> that flattered the <hi>Jews</hi> with an end of their <hi>Babylonian</hi> Captivity in two years, ſhall not himſelf live full two months, <hi>Jer.</hi> 28.3, 4, 16, 17. I will commend to your conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Prophet <hi>Jeremy's</hi> complaint to God, and Gods anſwer to the Prophet, Jer. 14.13. <hi>Ah Lord God, Behold the Prophets ſay unto them, ye ſhall not ſee the ſword, neither ſhall ye have famine, but I will give you aſſured peace in this place.</hi> 15. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord concerning the Prophets that propheſie in my name and I ſent them not, yet they ſay, ſword and famine ſhall not be in this Land, by ſword and famine ſhall thoſe Prophets be conſumed.</hi> 16. <hi>And the people to whom they propheſie, ſhall be caſt out in the ſtreets of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>becauſe of the famine and the ſword, and they ſhall have none to bury them, their wives, nor their ſons, nor their daughters: for I will pour their wickedneſs upon them.</hi> God will not perform the deceitful promiſes of the Miniſters of Satan, but he will certainly execute his threatnings againſt them: that their end ſhall be according to their works. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.15. In a word, when Hell ſwallowed up quick ſome wicked Miniſters for flattering the people, that they were holy enough; and for charging thoſe that were more ſtrict, that they took too much upon them, the Text ſayes, <hi>All</hi> Iſrael <hi>that were round about them, fled at the cry of them, for they ſaid, leſt the earth ſwallow us up alſo,</hi> Numb. 16.3.32, 33, 34.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:45958:12"/>
               <p n="2">2. Much more <hi>ſhould we make it our buſineſs to improve the death of good Miniſters.</hi> We read 1 Sam. 25.1. <hi>When</hi> Samuel <hi>dyed, all the Iſraelites were gathered together, and lamented him.</hi> Some ſuppoſe <hi>Saul</hi> himſelf was a Mourner at the Funeral. But if that be a miſtake, I am ſure this is not, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.14. <hi>When</hi> Eliſha <hi>was fallen ſick of his ſickneſs whereof he dyed, Joaſh</hi> (one of the wicked Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for they were none of them good) came down unto him, <hi>and wept over his face, and ſaid, Oh my Father, my Father, the Chariot of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and the horſemen thereof.</hi> Chriſtians, 'Tis not enough to breathe out a ſigh, or to ſqueez out a tear, 'tis not enough to come fee a faithful Miniſter buried, as thoſe went to ſee Chriſt crucified, Luke 23.48. <hi>And all the people that came together to that ſight, ſmote their breaſts and returned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſtians, I muſt crave leave to be a little more plain and particular with you, for your improvement of this preſent ſtroke, in the Lords taking from us this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious man of God. The <hi>fence</hi> of Gods Vineyard (as to men) is but a tottering hedge, and God hath pull'd up one of the <hi>beſt</hi> ſtakes of it. The <hi>Wall</hi> of Chriſts Garden is at preſent (as to men) but a bowing Wall, and God hath taken down one of the beſt <hi>Buttereſſes</hi> of it. But why ſhould I ſpeak thus to you? I can tell you nothing but what you know better than I: and what I ſhall ſay, 'tis in order to the preſſing of what I hope you will do better than I. The truth is I muſt needs break out into that of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> Neh. 13.22. <hi>O my God, ſpare me according to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thy mercy.</hi> I fall ſhort of what I ſhall mention of him: and yet more ſhort of what I ſhall preſs upon you. I have ſomething particularly to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45958:13"/>charge-upon all ſorts of hearers, and Oh that it may take impreſſion, and have an abiding upon your hearts. 1 Chron. 29.18. <hi>O Lord God, keep this for ever in the imagination of the thoughts of the heart of thy people, and prepare their heart unto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. You that were the dear <hi>Relations</hi> of this eminent Saint, that have the <hi>firſt</hi> ſmart of the ſtroke, I would give you the <hi>firſt</hi> of my poor counſel. Was he ſuch a <hi>Husband,</hi> that what ever is deſirable in that relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may be truly affirmed to have been found in him. Was his love to your <hi>perſon,</hi> and his love to your <hi>ſoul</hi> ſo exceeding great, that it makes your loſs very hard to be born? I ſhall ſay no more but this; Let your eminently gracious carriage through the remainder of your life, be an exemplary demonſtration, that you had ſuch a help about twenty ſix years: and then I dare aſſure you, that you will have the comfortable ſenſe of that ſuitable Promiſe, Iſa. 54.5. <hi>Thy Maker is thine Husband, (the Lord of Hoſts is his Name) and thy Redeemer the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>the God of the whole earth ſhall he be called.</hi> To you that had <hi>ſuch</hi> a Brother, that was more than a Brother, I would beg of you <hi>ſuch</hi> an univerſal imitation, ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable emulation, that both God and man may through Chriſt call you every one by the name of <hi>Goode</hi> that you may be <hi>ſeriouſly</hi> good, <hi>blameleſly</hi> good, <hi>exemplarily</hi> good.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To you that have in a <hi>ſpecial</hi> manner ſate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Miniſtry, that through this golden Pipe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the teachings of God, and the influences of his Spirit: to you I commend but this one thing, I will not clog your memories, but preſs upon your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences this one thing, <hi>Live over what you have heard from him:</hi> I doubt not, but ſhould I diſcourſe with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45958:13"/>any of you, he that could ſcarce ſpeak ſenſe in other things, would be an <hi>Orator</hi> in his commendations: and thoſe that are beſt able to judge, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their judgement in the moſt florid ſtrain, would (not only modeſtly, but) heartily confeſs, his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial worth was above their commendations. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, you are the perſons, of whom I would have it ſaid concerning him, as 'twas ſaid of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> concerning <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. That your whole Congregation is a large <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of his commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſent forth into the world, well known, and read of all that know you, that you are Chriſts Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle written by his Miniſtry, that Chriſt by his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath written the bleſſed characters of his grace in your hearts, that is legible in your lives, that what ever his Miniſtry was to others, the efficacy of it is ſeen among <hi>You.</hi> And as the bleſſed <hi>Apoſtle</hi> beſpeaks the <hi>Philippians,</hi> Chap. 4.9. <hi>Thoſe things which ye have both learned, and received, and heard, and ſeen in him, do: and the God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. To you that are of this <hi>Pariſh,</hi> though you have not that cauſe of complaint, which many have upon their change of Miniſters, yet I cannot but charge theſe things upon you.</p>
               <p>Remember how he came to you: wherein there was not only your importunity, but the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, as a weighty caſe of conſcience, by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Reverend Miniſters of the City, to whom it was referred; that he was as it were <hi>torn</hi> away from a People, to whom his labours and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was moſt acceptable: where when he preached his <hi>Farewell Sermon,</hi> there was not only a flood of tears; but the <hi>Lamentations of many were ſo loud,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45958:14"/>that his own voyce could ſcarcely be heard.</hi> Yet to you he came, as 'twas judged he was in conſcience bound, for greater advantage of doing good here, than another might probably have; that you ſitting under the Miniſtry of <hi>ſuch a Son,</hi> of <hi>ſuch a Father,</hi> [I will thank that man that will ſhew me ſuch a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Son left in <hi>England</hi>] Oh what Chriſtians was it expected you would be? Have you anſwered the expectation of God and man in this matter? If not: How are you able to think of it? and to ſtand under your own thoughts? that ſuch an one, who many a time hath adventured to go into the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> when others judged it more proper he ſhould have gone into his <hi>Bed?</hi> That ſuch an one, who hath done <hi>ſo</hi> much, I cannot ſay <hi>how</hi> much for the ſaving of your ſouls? That ſuch an one, who hath ſpent his <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and <hi>life,</hi> and now layes his <hi>bones</hi> amongſt you, ſhall ſtand forth in the laſt day, and ſay, <hi>Lord I could not perſwade them to come to Chriſt, that they might have life?</hi> I did not do the work of the Lord negligently amongſt them, their conſciences can witneſs? How many of you that ſhall ſleep with him in the ſame <hi>dormitory,</hi> will be afraid of him, when you ſhall riſe together, and go together to Judgement? Could we ſuppoſe there might be a Dialogue between you in your paſſage from the Grave to the Barr, how would you then ſay,</p>
               <p>Oh that we had taken your counſel; you ſpake many a good word from Chriſt to us, Cannot you now ſpeak one good word to Chriſt for us? Would he not give you ſome ſuch anſwer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I told you that ſin would be bitter in the latter end, but you would venture it: I told you, your good opinion of ſin would not hold, but you would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45958:14"/>it: I told you of the account you muſt give, but you would not regard it: My Commiſſion is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, I cannot make you one offer of Chriſt more, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance might have helpt you, but now, what repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance you have will be part of your torment: I have dealt plainly with you before, and I dare not flatter you now, I cannot ſpeak a word for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh what would you reply to this? Do you not think you ſhould cry out in ſome ſuch, but more doleful language, Oh pity me, dear Sir, pity me, I well remember that I have heard and ſeen you pity poor undone ſinners, and in a moſt melting manner, you have almoſt turned my heart within me, to hear you plead with <hi>them,</hi> and with <hi>God</hi> for them, you have loſt none of your Graces, the <hi>Judge</hi> is your friend, he will deny you nothing. Speak one word for me, that I may have a little <hi>more</hi> time: Oh that God would ſpare me a little. But alas, what would the anſwer be?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>'Tis true neighbour what you ſay, I have pitied you heartily, and prayed for you many a night when you were faſt aſleep, or worſe employed, I have pleaded with you, till you were angry at my impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, and I have begged mercy for you, as for mine own ſoul; but I can do ſo no more, I have not loſt my Graces, but they muſt henceforth be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in another kind of exerciſe: I thankfully grant, the Judge is my friend, but I muſt withal tell you, I muſt juſtifie his denying mercy to thoſe that refuſed it; every thing of Religion was bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome to you, and now you are going where you ſhall never be troubled with it more; you have no cauſe to complain of any but your ſelf, you have had
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45958:15"/>time, and then cared not how you ſpent it, and now the Judge hath ſworn, that time ſhall be no longer: Have you therefore any more to ſay?</hi> Oh that I might be but once heard before I am eternally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by an irreverſible ſentence.</p>
               <p>I grant all that you ſay, my conſcience is now awake; I have other thoughts of ſin and Chriſt, of Heaven and Hell, than ever I had while upon earth; might I have a little reſpite; I would ſpend every moment of it about the working out of my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Oh that God would truſt me once more, I confeſs I have broke all the promiſes I have made, but I have now other kind of experiences than ever I had before; and therefore by all the arguments that your ſelf have uſed to me, with the utmoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity that ever poor creature begged any thing, I beg that you would now befriend me; beg me but <hi>one</hi> hours reſpite, but <hi>one</hi> hour to plead for my poor ſoul unto eternity. To all this and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more that extream anguiſh will force from you, you can expect but ſuch a kind of anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I grant your caſe is dreadful, and I cannot blame you to be earneſt to alter it, but it is now too late; the time of life is the only time of grace and mercy: the experience your ſoul hath had during its ſeparation from the body atteſts this: I know miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cannot but cry out, though to no purpoſe, and 'tis inhumanity on earth to inſult over thoſe that are miſerable, but I muſt tell you, thoſe that are moſt compaſſionate cannot now pity you. Thoſe that with tears and importunities beg'd mercy for you as for themſelves, now praiſe God for his moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45958:15"/>vengeance; and God himſelf will laugh at your deſtruction; your day is paſt, the gulf is fixt,</hi> (Luke 16.20.) <hi>and there's no remedy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be intreated therefore forthwith to conſider of theſe things: I muſt tell you, that though I have ſuppoſed this tranſient Dialogue, yet unleſs while you live, you make ſure work for Heaven, you will not afterwards have ſo long a reſpite for ſo ſhort a Diſcourſe: Behold <hi>NOW</hi> is the accepted time: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>NOW</hi> is the day of ſalvation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And now, my <hi>Dear Brethren of the Miniſtry,</hi> know you not that there is a <hi>Seer</hi> and a great man faln this day in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and we are weak, though under ſome enlargement of liberty? The Proteſtant intereſt needs ſuch <hi>Champions:</hi> 'Twas a <hi>William Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker</hi> that gave the Beaſt a deadly wound in the <hi>Chair,</hi> and this <hi>William Whitaker,</hi> whoſe work lay moſt in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> was well able to ſtop the mouths of gainſayers. Practical godlineſs wants ſuch a <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> Acts 11.24. <hi>Who was a good man, and full of the Holy Ghoſt and Faith, and much people was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto the Lord.</hi> And alas my Brethren we want ſuch a <hi>Goſpel-Biſhop.</hi> Titus 1.7, 8, 9. <hi>Who was blameleſs as the Steward of God: not ſelf-willed, not ſoon angry, not given to wine; no ſtriker, not given to filthy lucre, but a lover of hoſpitality, a lover of good men, ſober, juſt, holy, temperate, holding faſt the faithful word,</hi> &amp;c. I do not remember that ever he came among us, but we were all ready to riſe up and call him bleſſed, his preſence was ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing. Should I trace him from his Cradle to his Grave, you will find nothing but what was lovely. Gal. 1.15, 16. <hi>It pleaſed God to ſeparate him from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45958:16"/>his Mothers womb, and to call him to his grace,</hi> there's none can name the time of his unregeneracy: <hi>and to reveal Chriſt to him,</hi> that he might preach <hi>Chriſt</hi> both in <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> and he <hi>conſulted not with fleſh and blood.</hi> In the fifteenth year of his age he was admitted in <hi>Emanuel Colledge;</hi> whoſe firſt <hi>Tutor</hi> gave him this direction, which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly obſerved, <hi>viz. To note every day what, and how much he ſtudied, that in after times reflecting on his life paſt, he might repent of the time he had loſt.</hi> While himſelf was a Pupill, he was as it were a <hi>Tutor</hi> to many <hi>Tutors</hi> of the <hi>Colledge,</hi> diverſe of the <hi>Fellows</hi> deſiring, and receiving direction from him in the <hi>Oriental</hi> Tongues. Dr. <hi>Holſworth</hi> then Maſter of the <hi>Colledge</hi> took ſuch notice of him while a <hi>Freſhman,</hi> that he gave him the Keyes of the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge-Library,</hi> and appointed him Tasks in tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Euſtatius</hi> upon <hi>Homer,</hi> wherein he did ſo much, as is ſcarce to be imitated. But why ſhould I be ſo particular in the former part of his life? Let it ſuffice to ſay in ſhort, <hi>His Piety, Learning, ſweetneſs of Diſpoſition, Candour and Ingenuity were ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, that he was loved and honoured of all that knew him;</hi> and was for his time one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Ornaments</hi> and <hi>Tutors</hi> of the Univerſity; I may ſay ſomething of him like to what was ſaid of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> Acts 7.22. he was learned in all neceſſary learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and was, in all he undertook, <hi>a workman that needed not to be aſhamed.</hi> In the twenty fourth year of his age he entred into the Miniſtry, and how he hath fulfilled it, you all know. He took the counſel the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> gave to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Give thy ſelf wholly to them.</hi> A Miniſters whole
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45958:16"/>being ſhould be in his Miniſtry; his <hi>ſoul,</hi> his <hi>body,</hi> his <hi>times,</hi> all his <hi>graces,</hi> all his <hi>learning,</hi> all his <hi>ſtudies,</hi> all his <hi>intereſts,</hi> all laid out in the work of <hi>THE</hi> Miniſtry, in the work of <hi>HIS</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, in the work of <hi>HIS OTHER MENS</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry: His deſerved fame for this is not confined within the narrow Seas. I think I may ſay, you cannot ſhew me throughout <hi>England</hi> ſuch a <hi>Schola illuſtris</hi> for forreign Divines; his houſe was for many years full, ſeldome at any time empty, of <hi>Candidates</hi> in Divinity, who returned ſo accompliſht for their work, that I fear not to ſay, They, and the Congregations, where they exerciſe their Miniſtry, will bleſs God to eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for his <hi>non-ſuch</hi> help. I could name other things, that would be <hi>excellencies</hi> in others, that were ſo <hi>natural</hi> to him, that ſhould I mention them, I muſt preſent you with a <hi>Journal</hi> of his life: I will therefore ſingle out but one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; he was ſuch a <hi>Peace-Preacher,</hi> and <hi>Peace-Maker,</hi> where ever he came, that at <hi>Horn-Church</hi> where he was Miniſter, he ended a Controverſie of many years ſtanding, about which they had expended above a <hi>thouſand</hi> pound. What's there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be done by us, now, in our circumſtances upon the conſideration of ſuch a pattern? My dear Brethren, I would be truly ſenſible of my unfitneſs to adviſe, but ſeeing this ſervice is <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectedly</hi> caſt upon me, I would be your <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer</hi> in theſe things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Let it be your great care, <hi>jointly</hi> and <hi>ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,</hi> that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> may be as little a loſer, as it is poſſible by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45958:17"/>Oh that the Spirit of <hi>Elijah</hi> may be doubled upon our <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s, that as the fewer hands, the more work, ſo we may find, the more <hi>work,</hi> the more <hi>grace;</hi> the more <hi>skill,</hi> the more <hi>ſtrength;</hi> that we may experience, God can ſave ſouls by <hi>few,</hi> as well as by <hi>many;</hi> by the <hi>Minor,</hi> as well as by the <hi>Major</hi> Prophets. Let me a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more then allude to 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. that as his Miniſtry who is gone away from us was glorious, much more may yours that remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, be glorious.</item>
                  <item>2. Lets make it our buſineſs to be as much Miniſters out of the Pulpit, as in it. The well diſcharge of the Miniſtry is an intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble drudgery to a carnal heart: to have not only our Sermons, but our occaſional diſcourſes; to have not only our words, but our ſilence ſpeak us Miniſters of Chriſt; to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes upon our watch (if I may ſo ſpeak) ſleeping and waking, that is, to ſleep no more than is neceſſary to our watchfulneſs; who that is not gracious (I had almoſt ſaid) eminently gracious, can endure it? At all times, in all places, to imitate our great Shepheard, who was <hi>anointed with the Holy Ghoſt, and with Power, who went about doing good, and healing all that were op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed of the Devil: for God was with him,</hi> Acts 10.38. Brethren, to have all our Sermons ſmell of the Lamp, and that Lamp ſupplyed from the Spirit of Grace; certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45958:17"/>'twas not without great cauſe, that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> puts an additional Petition into his prayer for <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> beyond all the Petitions for all the Churches he wrote unto, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. <hi>Titus</hi> 1.4. 'Twas only <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> for others, 'twas Grace, <hi>MERCY,</hi> and Peace for Miniſters, plainly ſhewing that they want <hi>Mercy,</hi> more than any others in the world.</item>
                  <item>3. Let's induſtriouſly live up to what is by all expected from us. God, Angels, and men, and thoſe both good and bad do all expect great things from us.</item>
                  <item>1 Cor. 4.9. <hi>God hath made us a ſpectacle to the world.</hi> We are in a more ſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than others under the jealous eye of God.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Good</hi> Angels that obſerve us, one of them told <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Divine, I am thy fellow-ſervant, and of thy Brethren the Prophets,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do not any thing unbecoming thee, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.9.</item>
                  <item>And when ever we ſtand before the Lord, <hi>bad</hi> Angels are ready at our right hand to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt us, and to accuſe us for any corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he ſees in us, <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.1, 3.</item>
                  <item>Good men they are commanded to obſerve us as Copies to write after, Heb. 13.7. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them which have the rule over you, who have ſpoken unto you the word of God, whoſe faith follow,</hi> &amp;c. And we are commanded ſo to walk, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. that they which <hi>ſpeak againſt us as evil doers,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45958:18"/>may by our good works that they ſhall behold, glorifie God in the day of viſitation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Brethren, ſome may ſpeak <hi>more</hi> good of you, than you dare owne; Look upon it as Gods gracious <hi>Stratagem,</hi> to provoke you to live up to it: Some ſpeak <hi>more</hi> ill of you, than you deſerve; Look upon it as the <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>only</hi> way to confute them by an heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converſation. <hi>Do nothing through ſtrife or vain glory,</hi> Phil. 2.3, 4, 5. but with an univerſal conformity unto Jeſus Chriſt.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Pardon me, dear Brethren, I have trangreſſed my bounds in thus ſpeaking to you; but 'tis on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſet your own thoughts and graces on work, to do more than I can preſs you to.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A word to <hi>all</hi> that this day hear me. It is but a few <hi>minutes</hi> ere death will ſtop our mouths that we ſhall ſpeak to you no more. Methinks, if thoſe that lived above twice ſo many <hi>hundred</hi> years, as men do now <hi>ſcores,</hi> counted their life by <hi>dayes,</hi> Gen. 5.27. the time we live ſhould be counted by <hi>hours,</hi> and then of the hour of our life, how few <hi>minutes,</hi> are remaining, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is my advice to all.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Make that uſe of Miniſters while they live, that you will wiſh you had made of them when they are dead.</hi> We read <hi>Luke</hi> 17.20. the Phariſces demanded of Chriſt, <hi>when the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God ſhould come:</hi> they expected the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> but would not owne <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be <hi>He;</hi> they reckoned he would come in more ſtately man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45958:18"/>Chriſt was in their eye contemptible: but Chriſt ſaith, Verſe 22. <hi>The dayes will come, when ye ſhall deſire to ſee one of the dayes of the Son of man, and ye ſhall not ſee it. q. d.</hi> As much as you overlook me now, you would be glad I would make the ſame offer hereafter. Luke 19.42. <hi>Oh that thou hadſt known, at leaſt in this thy day, the things which belong unto thy peace: but now they are hid from thine eyes.</hi> How many are ready to fancy, could they have the ſcattered excellencies of all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters meet in one, that the ſame man were a <hi>Moſes</hi> for Prayer, a <hi>Paul</hi> for Preaching, a <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> for frighting ſinners to repentance, a <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> for comforting drooping Converts; an <hi>Apollos</hi> for convincing gainſayers; a <hi>Jeremy</hi> for weeping over the incorrigible; in ſhort, could you have ſuch a one, as there's never a one in the world, then you would <hi>attend</hi> his Miniſtry, <hi>love</hi> his converſe, <hi>take</hi> his counſell, <hi>follow</hi> his example, be <hi>glad</hi> of his help towards Heaven; though by the way, <hi>you</hi> are miſerably miſtaken in all this: for you have <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Chriſt and his Apeſtles, and faithful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters that watch for your ſouls, as thoſe that muſt give an account, if you benefit not by theſe, Chriſt tells you plainly, neither would you be perſwaded, though a <hi>Saint</hi> from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or a <hi>damned</hi> Perſon from Hell ſhould tell you what <hi>may</hi> be enjoyed, or what <hi>muſt</hi> be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in thoſe places, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.31. Chriſtians, the Lord hath told us, that the wiſdom of God ſends us thoſe faithful Miniſters who <hi>deſerve</hi> the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45958:19"/>beſt, but <hi>receive</hi> the worſt entertainment, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.49. Be not ſo proud, as to think your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom could contrive a better method of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or fitter perſons to publiſh it: make uſe of the helps God affords you, while they live, that you may not be ready to go to the Devil to ſpeak with that <hi>Samuel</hi> when dead, whom you ſlighted while alive.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Make that uſe of Miniſters while you are well, that you will wiſh you had made of them when you are ſick.</hi> Oh what alteration doth <hi>one</hi> hours heart-ſickneſs make in mens thoughts! Then thoſe that ſcarce ever ſpake <hi>of</hi> a Miniſter, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs with ſcorn, that ſcarce ever ſpake <hi>to</hi> a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, unleſs (at beſt) in complement, yet when they apprehend they ſhall dye, then ſend for a Miniſter, then they will do any thing, when the truth is, they are fit for nothing; then they will hear you ſpeak of ſalvation, could you but tell them how they might be ſaved by miracle, to have a happy death, out of a wicked life: then they will tell you, how holy they will be if they live; though nothing more ordinary, than for thoſe who repent <hi>only</hi> when they are ſick, to repent of their repentance, ſo ſoon as they are well. Now therefore in time of health and ſtrength make uſe of your Miniſters, that you may not fruitleſly mourn at the laſt. <hi>When your fleſh, and your body are conſumed, and ſay, how have I hated inſtruction, and my heart deſpiſed reproof? and have not obeyed the voyce of my Teachers, nor enclined mine ear to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45958:19"/>them that inſtructed me?</hi> Prov. 5.11, 12. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, we are <hi>Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us; we</hi> now <hi>pray you in Chriſts ſtead be ye reconciled to God,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.20. We would give you all the help we can, that you may not receive the Goſpel of Chriſt in vain, delay not to ſet about the <hi>things that accompany ſalvation</hi> one moment longer; for <hi>behold, now is the accepted time, behold now is the day of ſalvation,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.2. Now live as thoſe that heartily believe, it is not long that either <hi>we</hi> ſhall Preach, or <hi>you</hi> ſhall hear the Word of Salvation. Hearken therefore <hi>while it is called to day, leſt any of you be hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned through the deceitfulneſs of ſin.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
